Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is כ"ז, Chaf Zayin,
27, and we pick up at the bottom of כ"ו עמוד ב'.
Chaf Vav Amud Bet. Briefly review some of the important things we
said over שבת Shabbos because the גמרא Gemara here is discussing
which
type of men are included, are part of this prohibition, the category
of סוטה Sotah in terms of who her husband could be and
who the suspected adulterer could be.
And the theme that we saw yesterday over שבת, Shabbat, which is
just so central, is the focus on the זרע, Zera, which appears
a number of times. It says ונקתה ונזרעה זרע, V'nikesah v'nizre'ah zera,
she'll be cleansed and give forth seed. It says ושכב איש אותה
שכבת זרע, V'shachav ish osah shichvat zera, a man slept with her,
a sleeping of seed. And we pointed out at that time the
point of the רמב"ן, Ramban, that a lot of the jealousy of
the סוטה Sotah might be fueled by the man's deep-seated concern or
anxiety over whether his wife, not just is sleeping with another man,
but is impregnated by another man, whether he'll be raising another man's
children, and hence the emphasis on זרע. Zera. We pointed out that
the
in a way, something I don't think I pointed out before, but
that the whole ritual of סוטה Sotah or the effect of the
water, right? If she's cleansed, she gives forth a seed. And if
she's not, what happens is that the water goes into her and
makes her belly swell, which is a type of a perverse pregnancy.
So there's a concern about whose זרע Zera is in her, and
the water becomes almost a type of a liquid going in in
the sort of, to the same place through the opposite orifice, like
in the opposite direction. And if she's guilty, it has this, it
creates this perverse type of זרע. Zera. And if she's innocent, then
it's ונקתה ונזרעה זרע. V'nikesah v'nizre'ah zera. And she actually has a
child, which the גמרא Gemara discussed yesterday. If she was, if she
was עקרה Akarah or זקנה, Zekenah, sterile, now she's pregnant, if she
had a hard time giving birth, she has an easier time giving
birth to children. So the question becomes, right? The question becomes, what's
the halakhic significance of that? So interestingly, on the one hand, we
found out that even if a woman is עקרה Akarah or זקנה,
Zekenah, sterile, she still could be in the פרשה Parsha of סוטה,
Sotah, even though there would be no chance she would be pregnant.
The only question was an אילונית, Aylonit, who was more, she was
categorically excluded, and even that was debated. On the other hand, even
if the that so now on the other, similarly, meaning what we
wind up doing is, again and again and again, we sort of
bracket the significance of זרע, Zera, even though it's very dominant both
in the words of the פסוקים Pesukim and as I've just described
in the sort of experience or description of the power of the
ritual or the effects of the water. So on the other, so
similarly, excuse me, if the husband is not able to be מזריע,
Mazria, he's not able to ejaculate, nevertheless that doesn't affect it. So
there's no, you know, the seed is sort of clearly not going
to be his seed or whatever. Maybe that makes it worse, I
don't know, maybe it makes it better. At least he knows it's
not his child anyway. By the way, none of this assumes she's
pregnant. I'm just saying that when she is suspected of committed adultery,
there's that anxiety that's lying below it. So even if the man,
the husband can't have זרע, Zera, we learned out. And now what
we turn to yesterday,
the עמוד ב' Amud Bet of yesterday, was that even if the
suspected adulterer can't have זרע, Zera, שחוף, Shachuf, which is explained also
as a man who is unable to be מזריע, Mazria, to ejaculate
and so on. And nevertheless, we learn from the
פסוקים Pesukim that even without that, he is in, it is in
the פרשה Parsha of סוטה. Sotah. So in all these different ways,
even if she can't have a child, even if he can't be
מזריע, Mazria, even if the suspected man can't be מזריע, Mazria, the
הלכה למעשה Halakha l'maaseh brackets the significance of זרע, Zera, which very
much dominates in the פסוקים. Pesukim. So that's one series of things
that we looked at yesterday. And then the other focus was, okay,
but who is meant by being excluded by this word of מי
שאינו איש? Mi she'eino ish? And it goes through a couple of
possibilities. It says it's not coming to exclude a man who can't
be מזריע, Mazria, again connecting manhood with virility, because that person is
included if she's suspected of sleeping with such a man. It can't,
it comes to exclude a non-Jew, which would be funny to put
in that phase anyway, because that person also is included if she's
suspected or actually the סוטה. Sotah. And the final person or not
even person, whatever, the final one who is in the category of
מי שאינו איש, Mi she'eino ish, which we ended with yesterday, was
בהמה. Behemah. If she's suspected of actually an act of bestiality, even
though of course that would be a very serious sin, but it
would not be that a presumably that idea of
וכי תשטה אשתו, V'ki tisteh ishto, she's seen as doing some perverse
act, but
not
necessarily. And the last point I'll say in this חזרה chazarah and
then Michael has a question is, interestingly, it never suggested another point
I made yesterday, never suggested מי שאינו איש mi she'eino ish is
a woman, and that is because for halakhic purposes,
gay sex, or sex between two women, let me just say it
that way, sex between two women is not considered an act of
sex. Halakhically, the act of sex is always defined as a penis
penetrating either the vagina or the anus. So therefore, that's why you
can have a discussion about sex between two men, a discussion prohibition
about sex between two men, but not about sex between two women
because halakhically that's not defined actually as sex. So that doesn't become
part of the suggestion. So ultimately what we're left with is בהמה
היא beheimah hi because that actually can be, okay, it's not a
human penis but it still is defined as the act of sex.
And one thing, final thing I should point out to this is
that my colleague Rabbi Shmuel Herzfeld showed me that there's
some אחרון, acharon, I don't remember who it is, I don't remember
the date, but anyway, who basically, maybe it was even, I don't
know, anyway, who basically wanted to say that מי שאינו איש mi
she'eino ish also included like a shade, which is, which is interesting
because it was a question about a woman whose husband was away
and then she was pregnant and she said she'd become impregnated by
a shade. So the fact that this מי שאינו איש mi she'eino
ish get her out of the problem, at least that was her
claim, but it's the type of a claim that could only have
been accepted in a society in which believed that it was possible,
right? So in that type of place, well, okay, it's אינו איש
eino ish and that's somehow of a way of allowing her to
continue to live with her husband. Yes.
So
I'm just trying to understand, so in the normal case, assuming she's
guilty and has no זכות, zechut, she wouldn't explode, but she would
just basically die.
Well, that's not clear that she would, what do you mean? If
she's guilty, her belly would swell, whether that would lead immediately or
over time to her death is never spelled out explicitly in the
פסוקים pesukim and not even clear in
the גמרא. Gemara.
So they didn't necessarily even think she'd die according to what the
גמרא Gemara was saying. Correct. Okay. And then in the case of
we said that you can do, make a סוטה Sotah a man
who cannot have kids, a sterile man can go through the whole
process with his wife and she has to drink. Then if she's
innocent, what would be her ברכה? berachah? She can't have kids from
him anyway.
Well, that's a good question. Yeah, I don't know. I don't know.
Maybe he'd be blessed although that'd be bizarre. I don't know. That's
a good question. Yeah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara so let's pick
up now with our answer about the המה. hahemah. So it's almost
exactly opposite where the תוספות Tosafot says למעוטי, le-a-tu-ye, I guess about
twenty-five lines from the bottom, so we got a little bit of
a little bit of a bit of a mouth to cover today.
ואידך למעוטי מאי, ve-idach le-a-tu-ye mai, so what is אינו איש eino
ish coming to exclude? What type of case is that she's suspected
of
with whom would she be suspected of that's אינו איש eino ish
that would not make her סוטה? Sotah? אמר רב פפא למעוטי בהמה,
amar Rav Papa le-a-tu-ye beheimah,
if she's suspected of an act of bestiality, I guess the קינוי
kinui would also have to be, I don't want to see you
going in private with that בהמה. beheimah. I don't know. Anyway, דאין
זנות בבהמה de-ein zenut be-beheimah because that's not considered fornication, which again,
does not mean it's not a prohibition, right? It's חייב מיתה, chayav
mitah, an act of bestiality, but it's not in the category of
זנות. zenut. It's not normal sexuality and it's not a normal type
of an act that if she's מזנה, mezaneh, she, you know, cheats
on her husband. It would not be seen in the same way.
אמר ליה רבא מפרזיקיא לרב אשי amar leh Rava mi-Farzikaya le-Rav Ashi
מנא הני מילי דאמרי רבנן אין זנות בבהמה, mena hanei milei de-amri
rabbanan ein zenut be-beheimah,
where do you know that this is not considered to be an
act of זנות? zenut? Whatever this is, this is a bizarre act,
but it's not an act of זנות. zenut. Okay,
דכתיב, de-chtiv, thank you so much, לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב
בית ה' אלקיך. lo tavi etnan zonah u-mechir kelev beit Hashem Elokecha.
Do not be an אתנן זונה, etnan zonah, a gift that was
given to a prostitute. So if a person paid a prostitute with
a sheep, then that sheep cannot be used as a קרבן. korban.
ומחיר כלב u-mechir kelev is if a sheep was exchanged for a
dog, it can't be used as a קרבן, korban, although the פשטני,
pashtanei, although scholars say that ומחיר כלב u-mechir kelev might refer to
actually the money paid to a male prostitute and it might be
a euphemism. But that's not the גמרא's Gemara point right now. ותניא
אתנן כלב ומחיר זונה, ve-tanya etnan kelev u-mechir zonah, however, if it
was money given for sleeping with a dog, or it was a
money exchanged with a זונה, zonah, which is a little funny, how
do you how do you buy a זונה zonah with money? So
רש"י Rashi sort of says we're talking about selling for example a
slave woman for the purpose of זנות. zenut. In those cases מותרין,
mutarin, they're not prohibited in the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, שנאמר גם
שניהם, she-ne'emar gam sheneihem, the two of them, שנים ולא ארבע, shenayim
velo arba, only those two. So since there is no concept of
אתנן כלב, etnan kelev, money paid for sleeping with a dog, it's
not labeled as sort of, you know, a money paid for sex.
So you see that it's not considered to be זנות. zenut. It's
an obviously prohibited act, you know, but it is not considered in
the same category of like sexual sin in the same way, right?
Interesting question for example, you know, what exactly does it mean it's
not זנות? zenut? What הלכה halacha is זנות? zenut? Right? So in
our case, the question would be whether that makes it considered like
a betrayal of the husband? Right? Nobody's saying you're not חייב מיתה
chayav misa for it, okay? But to say there's not a concept
of אתנן כלב ethnan kelev means what? That it's not considered, that
has nothing to do with a husband. That's money paid for a
prostitute or whatever. So what does that have to do? That means
that it's not considered some type of a sexual act? It's some
weird act but it's not a sexual act? What about is it
יהרג ואל יעבור? yehareg ve-al ya'avor? Is it in the, is it
in the גילוי עריות gilui arayos category? Right? So what exactly is
the meaning that it's not זנות? zenut? What's the halachic meaning of
that? Is not fully spelled out. I think that that's debated. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואלא שכבת זרע למה לי?
ve-ela shichvas zera lama li?
So שכבת זרע shichvas zera is not coming to exclude a man
who cannot be מזריע, mazria, suspected of a man who's unable to
be מזריע mazria is still in the category. What is it its
purpose? Right? I mean it factors so centrally and we've basically completely
bracketed it halachically. So what's its significance? So מבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaya
lei lichdetanya, what we learn in a ברייתא. braita. שכבת זרע, shichvas
zera, פרט לדבר אחר. perat le-davar acher. Oh, that's coming to exclude
a different thing. That was helpful. מאי דבר אחר, mai davar acher,
what's this other thing? אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshes, פרט לשקינא
לה שלא כדרכה. perat she-kina la she-lo ke-darkah.
Let's say he said, I don't want you to have you sleep
with this man in with an act of anal sex. Okay, so
in that case, and that's what she was suspected of. So that
wouldn't be שכבת זרע shichvas zera because what we're saying is the
act, the man doesn't have to be able to be מזריע, mazria,
but it has to be vaginal sex, a type of a physical
act that under other circumstances could lead to pregnancy. As opposed to
an act of sex which is normally in all other areas of
הלכה halacha defined as sex, anal sex, but it's not an act
that could ever lead to pregnancy. That somehow was a is an
excluded act of sex. Yes.
Anyway, I mean, it's seclusion. That's the purpose of קינוי kinuy and
סתירה. stira.
So apparently what we are learning is is that that the קינוי
kinuy could be not just don't go into seclusion with him, but
I don't want, I, yeah, I mean if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, I agree, normal קינוי kinuy is don't go in seclusion, but
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, where רש"י Rashi says, אל תסתרי
al tisteri first wide line at the bottom, אל תסתרי עמו להיבעל
שלא
כדרכה.
al tisteri imo le-hibael she-lo
ke-darkah. Do not go in seclusion for the purpose of having anal
sex.
But he could have said
it more
broadly, it would have covered it, right? Right. I don't know. Let's
say, who knows? Let's say it's some other case where it was
impossible for her to have vaginal sex. So the only thing she
was suspected of, what?
The גמרא's Gemara good at constructing those.
Yes, I right. Anyway, let's try to imagine that. If that was
the only possible act, okay? Now, the importance of that would still
be that there, that the only basis of excluding that because halachically
that's an act of sex. The only basis of excluding that is
that we still think that שכבת זרע shichvas zera is significant. So
somehow still in a broader categorical way rather than in a very
specific case, but nevertheless, it's still playing a role. Let's see if
the גמרא Gemara accepts it, which it does not. So
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said, שלא כדרכה,
she-lo ke-darkah, what, that type of sex? משכבי אשה כתיב, mishkevei ishah
ksiv, the sleepings of a woman and that teaches us that there
are two types of acts acts that are defined as sex, vaginal
and anal. So therefore, he says there is no way that it
would be excluded. So what's your ha- what's playing out in the
גמרא Gemara is can we have this idea of שכבת זרע shichvas
zera to have any real, you know, role here? At the end
of the day, we're saying that's really irrelevant and since it's defined
as an act of sex and it's an act of adultery and
so on, we're going to completely bracket the significance of שכבת זרע
shichvas zera even to limit us to act of sex A rather
than B. No, it can't play any role since halachically those are
the same from the perspective of adultery, they're going to be the
same from the perspective of the פרשה parsha of סוטה. sotah. Again,
sort of, you know,
marginalizing the idea that the concern of another man's seed is at
all relevant. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואלא ve-ela what what was
that
פסוק? pasuk? ואת זכר לא תשכב? ve-es zachar lo tishkav? Right, right,
exactly. So which is funny because in that context there's only one
act of sex, but the fact that that's considered a sleeping of
a woman, the anal sex of two men, shows you that that's
considered, right, an act of sex. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava,
פרט לשקינא לה דרך איברים. perat she-kina lah derech evarim. Ah, what
he said was don't have even any form of sex without like,
you know, with the oral or manual, any, you know, through the
limbs which are not which are not anal or vaginal. Okay, so
that's the case that's being excluded. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abaye, אביי Abaye said, that you need a פסוק pasuk to exclude?
That's not an act of adultery. פריצותא בעלמא היא, peritzusa be-alma hi,
that's just an act of of what, sexual looseness, what? Licentiousness, thank
you. ופריצותא מי אסר רחמנא? u-peritzusa mi asar Rachmana? And that's not
forbidden. Now, does it mean it's not forbidden? Not forbidden for a
man to sleep with a married woman, you know, or not sleep.
with have oral sex with a married woman, but it is not
halachically an act of adultery. Whatever it is, okay, it might be
a חשישי chashishi or it might be whatever, I'm serious, you know,
it's another— but nevertheless it is not the act of adultery and
therefore it would not make her forbidden to her husband and therefore
we're taking it for granted that you didn't need the פסוק, pasuk,
the word of שכבת זרע shichvat zera to exclude that. We're doing,
we're being very formalistic right now, right? Rather than thinking that סוטה
Sotah is something different emerging from his jealousy and therefore maybe a
focus on זרע, zera, you know, because then the flip side is
it's emerging from his jealousy, it could have included that I don't
care whether it's technically, you know, this type of sex or that
type of sex, I don't want you doing anything with this guy,
right? But we're saying no, we're being like we're excluding both a
broader and a narrower category and we're being very, you know, formalistic
that it's only what is halachically defined as adultery. Anything that's either
like but that's either, you know, broader than that or narrower than
that is not part of the discussion.
So therefore it doesn't matter, why should you need a פסוק pasuk
that's not technically an act of adultery? אלא אמר אביי פרט ושקינא
לה בנשיקה. Ella amar Abaye: Prat v'shikina lah b'neshika. Ah, no, here's
the case where the concern is or his warning was about נשיקה.
neshika. Now נשיקה neshika does not mean kissing. נשיקה neshika is a
euphemism, whatever. It means what is defined now that again that we're
being very definitional here about what's defined as an act of adultery
or an act of sex in all areas of הלכה. halacha. So
it is considered to be— the פסוק pasuk constantly uses the word
which it says— it says מקורה הערה. mekorah herah. He exposed her
nakedness. So what is the halachic word is הערה. ha'arah. So what's
הערה? ha'arah? So הערה ha'arah there's two definitions: one it's הכנסת עטרה,
hachnasat atarah, the very entering in of the tip of the penis
into the vagina, and the other is נשיקה, neshika, which is literally
the kissing of the genitals, which is the putting of the penis
basically against like, you know, the vaginal lips and so on. So
again, the whole lips idea, you know, is sort of the metaphor
of נשיקה. neshika. So therefore he's saying, 'Ah, so that's what it's
excluding.' It's excluding when it's just
נשיקה neshika of the genitals. So the גמרא Gemara says: הניחא למאן
דאמר הערה זו הכנסת עטרה. Haniicha l'man d'amar: ha'arah zu hachnasat atarah.
Fine, that we would understand that that's not an act of sex.
So that's consistent with the idea that הערה ha'arah is the entering
in of the crown. אבל נשיקה ולאו כלום היא. Aval neshika v'lav
klum hi. And therefore, but נשיקה neshika is not an act of
sex, פשיטא דאתי קרא למעוטי נשיקה. Pshita d'ati kra l'ma'utei neshika. That's
why it's excluding it. אלא למאן דאמר הערה זו נשיקה. Ella l'man
d'amar: ha'arah zu neshika. But if הערה ha'arah is that the kissing
of the genitals, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? So why would
the פסוק pasuk be excluding it? It is defined as an act
of sex. So by the way, interesting, תוספות Tosafot says, 'I don't
understand, it should be the opposite.' I would have said if normally
it is considered an act of sex, then you could understand why
the פסוק pasuk needed to exclude it, whereas if it's not normally
an act of sex, then why did the פסוק pasuk need to
exclude it? It was already excluded. But again, what the גמרא's Gemara
being completely consistent about is its refusal to think that סוטה Sotah
is any different than any other time, any other way in which
we would define the act of sex or act of adultery. So
there's no way in which the parameters of his jealousy or whatever
would be broader or narrower than what the actual act of adultery
is defined of in all other areas. So completely again, this really
gets back, everything gets back to that first משנה, mishnah, the discussion
on the first דף, daf, which is how much is this about
his jealousy and how much is this about an objective sort of
בית דין Beit Din concern that she committed adultery, right? And the
fact that the גמרא Gemara here is completely refusing to make it
about זרע, zera, to make it broader, to make it narrower, to
make it about any type of thing he might be concerned about,
and completely saying we have to apply the class categories is taking
his subjectivity completely out of it. But let's see what the final
answer is. Such
a rich דף daf here right now. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לעולם ושקינא לה דרך איברים. L'olam v'shikina lah derech eivarim.
Back to what we said before. He's not concerned that she's actually
having intercourse, but other forms like, you know, anal or vaginal, but
other forms of sex or sexual activity. ומהו דתימא בקפידא דבעל תליא
רחמנא. U'mahu d'teima: b'kpeida d'ba'al talya rachmana.
Now it goes exactly to that, this is exactly why I needed
שכבת זרע shichvat zera to exclude it. Because I might have said,
not what אביי Abaye said, פריצותא בעלמא. pritzuta be'alma. Fine, פריצותא בעלמא.
pritzuta be'alma.
But this is קינא לאשתו. kina l'ishto. So I might have reasonably
thought that this type of jealousy is included because he doesn't like
it and it's a form of sexual activity. So even if it's
not technically adultery, maybe he's entitled, בקפידא דבעל תליא מילתא. b'kpeida d'ba'al
talya milta. Maybe he's entitled to be jealous about this. ובעל קפיד.
U'ba'al kapid. And here he's angry about this. קא משמע לן. Ka
mashma lan. That that doesn't matter. That even if he's jealous, if
it's not actually an act of adultery, שכבת זרע shichvat zera tells
us it's not included. So at the end of the day, what
שכבת זרע shichvat zera wound up telling us is not, again, like
the רמב"ן Ramban said, that there's a special role here of his
anxiety around another man's זרע, zera, and it's not telling us that
it's, you know, and therefore we would exclude cases where or the
other man couldn't be מזריע mazria or she couldn't have conceived or
whatever. And at the other hand, it's also not telling us, what
it is telling us, I should say, what it is telling us
is to exclude cases where he's concerned even beyond normal acts of
sex. So at the end of the day, שכבת זרע shichvas zera
winds up where we said once the dust settles, we wind up
saying that סוטה Sotah is no different than any, the only things
that fall into סוטה Sotah are things that in the rest of
the התורה Torah fall within the narrow definition of adultery. Not broader,
not narrower, exactly that narrow definition. So if he can't be מזריע,
mazria, it doesn't matter, it's still an act of sex. And if
it's things that aren't an act of sex, it doesn't matter because
it's not adultery. It's only things that are defined as adultery, which
by the way gets back, I'll just remind people, that the whole
central issue here around זרע zera played out, I mentioned this before
but it's worth mentioning, in the debate between רב משה Rav Moshe
and the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer about the permissibility of artificial insemination
using another man's semen. So רב משה Rav Moshe said like fine,
they're able to do פרו ורבו, pru u'revu, whatever, you're able to
have children. And the ציץ אליעזר Tzitz Eliezer said no, it's like
כמעט, kimat, it's like adultery, and the children are כמעט kimat they're
ממזרים, mamzerim, because basically רב משה Rav Moshe said what do you
mean—like they didn't actually talk to one another, I'm reconstructing this like
the גמרא Gemara reconstructs debates that never happened. Anyway, so רב משה
Rav Moshe says there's no act of sex, there's no ממזרות, mamzeros,
there's no adultery without an act of sex. And the ציץ אליעזר
Tzitz Eliezer says no, the רמב״ן Ramban says שכבת זרע shichvas zera
that a central part to the concern of adultery or the act
of adultery is another man's זרע. zera. So even if it's without
an act of sex, and that would even be related to the
idea of ממזרות. mamzeros. So רב משה Rav Moshe basically said oh,
that's such a טרייף traif non-Jewish idea. So he said I only
פסקן pasken based on like, you know, values that are from within
the התורה. Torah. I don't know about people that get these values
from outside of the התורה. Torah. It's very bizarre, what do you
mean outside of the התורה? Torah? I mean, it says שכבת זרע,
shichvas zera, the רמב״ן Ramban says that's what's going on. But רב
משה Rav Moshe might have been saying that's all very nice, but
since when are we קראים Karaites or פשטנים? Pashtanim? הלכה halacha
completely brackets the meaning of שכבת זרע shichvas zera what we've just
seen in our דף. daf. It completely neutralized any meaning of שכבת
זרע. shichvas zera. So that's why רב משה Rav Moshe is able
to say if all you have is זרע zera and you don't
have sex, it's not relevant.
Yeah, which
on the other hand, it raises the bar for an executable offense
of adultery so high that you know, even if you see them
under the covers, you know, maybe they're not doing that.
That's true. Okay, that's true, it's very hard, it's very hard to
execute people. ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem.
Yes, and we'll see more of that soon when we get there.
But like in terms of what sex is considered, right? If it's,
you know, all these other things apparently are not sex.
Right, that is true, at least for the
חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa or whatever. Yeah. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, ישא
אדם—now, yisa adam here it does get an interesting transition because you
know we've been talking very much within this formal category of who's
a סוטה, Sotah, but what about women that aren't technically a סוטה
Sotah but like okay, but there's still questions and suspicions and what
does it do to the marriage? So if you remember about two
דפים dapim ago, we dealt with a case about a woman who's
עוברת על דת overes al das and whether the husband is allowed
to sort of forgive, you know, not forgive, forgo that and they
continue to live together? Does it require him, does she have to
be warned, does it require him to divorce her? So it's interesting
when we're also dealing with related phenomenon that aren't technically סוטה. Sotah.
So similarly, we have a very interesting discussion right here. אמר שמואל,
Amar Shmuel, ישא אדם דומא ואל ישא בת דומא. yisa adam dumah
v'al yisa bas dumah. A man should more be prepared to marry
a woman who is gossiped about and not her daughter. Okay, so
there's a married woman, people are gossiping about her that she's you
know she sleeps around, this and that. No, obviously no evidence, it's
just gossip. And the question is now she gets divorced or I
don't know or is widowed. Okay, so would you be more prepared
to marry such a woman or such a woman's daughter? Like most
people aren't marrying her or her daughter because of the suspicions. You
נעבעך, nebech, I don't know, are a guy that's having a hard
time finding a wife, okay? And so which of these two would
be preferable, you know, for to marry? So שמואל Shmuel says—דומא dumah
meaning gossip.
So
רש״י Rashi says, you look at רש״י, Rashi, נתענת ונדברת בפי כל
על ניאופיה.
nisanes
v'nidberes b'fi kol al nioofeiha.
So people are making like claims and talking, gossiping about her on
her acts of adultery. דומא dumah לשון כלסתה ודיבור, lashon kalsata v'dibbur,
like I mean in נידה, niddah, דומא עירך עלך סבך. dumah ircha
alayich savach.
The talking of your city has come on, has like risen, gotten
into you. והוא לאו חשד הוא, v'hu lav chashad hu,
there in that case it wasn't suspicions, אלא דיבור יתר, ela dibbur
yeser, just like yakking away. שהיו מידברים בה על חביבותא. she'hayu midbarim
bah al chavivusa.
That was the opposite, that people were talking about a certain woman
because of how dear she was. חביבותא דבא לה. chavivusa d'ba lah.
ואף כלסה לשון דיבור יתר הוא. v'af kalsa lashon dibbur yeser hu.
כלסה kalsa also means just excessive talk and chatter. לפיכך הוא נהפך
לשון שבח ולשון גנאי. l'fichach hu nehpach lashon shevach v'lashon genai. Okay,
so therefore כלסה kalsa can sometimes mean praise but can sometimes mean—normally
it means praise anyway.
Also someone else added that word כלסה kalsa has
an
Arabic cognate of the same thing. Meaning gossip? Okay.
So okay, so anyway, so better to...
Oh really? Oh interesting. Anyway, better to marry such a woman. Now,
halachically the point is that the mother, if she committed adultery, you're
not the man suspected of having committed adultery with her because then
you would know.
So basically, the point is that now the husband died, you want
to marry her, so halachically she's not forbidden, right? Okay, so maybe
she'll be at most she did commit adultery and she's forbidden to
her husband and to the other guy, right? Anyway, it's just gossip,
but even if it's true, she's not forbidden to you. Her daughter
on the other hand, if it's the might be a ממזרת. mamzeret.
Okay, so which one of them is it better to marry? The
woman with questionable character, okay, or fidelity. Now it's interesting, רש"י Rashi
says the reason you don't want to marry such a woman, רש"י
Rashi turns it very halachic. The reason you don't want to marry
such a woman is suspected adulteress is that then she'll commit adultery
once you're married to her and you won't know about it, and
then you'll wind up being עובר over because you'll be sleeping with
her when she'll be אסור assur to you. So it's like, I
mean I think before you got to that, there'd be reasons why
you wouldn't want to marry a woman who might commit adultery. Anyway,
so the question is, so there's one which the woman is questionable
character, I'd say that that's the bigger concern than any halachic problem
that will emerge, and the other is a questionable ממזרת. mamzeret. So
which one should you better marry? So אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, ישא
אדם דומה yisa adam duma better to marry her ולא ישא בת
דומה, v'lo yisa bat duma, שזו באה מטיפה כשרה, she-zu ba mi-tipa
ksheira, this woman came from a valid seed, so her status is
okay, וזו באה מטיפה פסולה, v'zu ba mi-tipa psula, the daughter might
be a ממזרת. mamzeret. Now even there, he's framing it more in
value terms than in halachic terms, right? To call her she's a
ספק ממזרת safeik mamzeret you wouldn't say טיפה פסולה, tipa psula, it
sounds more like it's the question you know like everybody asks like
why did אברהם Avraham want to send his servant over there to
ארם נהרים, Aram Naharaim, you know, was it basically like, oh well
he knew the people of the town and they had good character
or was it more like no, he basically just you know was
something a little bit more
like race-based or whatever and that's not the right word, but anyway,
you know, believing that in certain types of people biologically are more
you know better people. So similar type of a question here I
think, it's a question about if you wanted to frame it not
halachically, it's a question about observed character or possible character, and the
other part of like who are your you
know like what's your you know but what's the word I'm looking
for which isn't race and isn't biology, but anyway you know the
question about you know like like the people what? Inbred? Yeah no
like like like the attitude of people that like don't like גרים
gerim because they're not naturally born Jews, not because of any concern
about you know so it's a I guess it's race anyway what?
Nativist maybe anyway nativist maybe I'm trying to maybe look for a
better a nicer word than race but maybe that's it anyway it's
not exactly racist but the point is is that like is character
the problem or somehow you know
metaphysically born of a טריפה treif union you know is deeper metaphysical
issue in the soul of this child than the question of the
character of the mother. So you know I would have said it
again like character versus halachic ממזרת mamzeret but the phrase טיפה פסולה
tipa psula seems to speak more about like her the nature of
the soul will be corrupt because it came from such a union.
Okay, so anyway he says better to marry the mother.
רש"י Rashi what does רש"י Rashi
say?
Well I gotta tell you I didn't understand רש"י Rashi because רש"י
Rashi says רש"י Rashi says וזו באה מביאה פסולה, v'zu ba mi-bi'a
psula, first of all רש"י Rashi says first of all he doesn't
say טיפה פסולה tipa psula so he had a different גרסא girsa
number one right so טיפה פסולה tipa psula more emphasizes the you
know again like the the soul that was created through the conception.
Right so the other thing I don't understand about רש"י Rashi is
שמא מעובד כוכבים וממזר, shema me-oved kochavim u-mamzer, what does רש"י Rashi
mean? Who cares if the who cares if the man she slept
with was a non-Jew or a ממזר? mamzer? The child's a ממזר
mamzer right? So like רש"י Rashi seems to say no the question
is that the semen of the man who impregnated her might be
problematic right? What do you mean? I mean maybe in a way
רש"י Rashi is reinforcing that's actually an answer I didn't understand רש"י
Rashi what do you mean maybe the child's if she slept with
another man the child's a ממזר mamzer so maybe again that's the
point it's not just the halachic issue of the child being a
ממזר mamzer the father might be somebody who you don't know you
know who the father is and the father might be somebody who's
of a bad seed. So again it's very interesting it's not the
question of halachic ממזר mamzer versus character of the mother it's character
of the mother versus biology of the girl you know and the
and you know what that does to her character at a deep
metaphysical level. Okay? Okay so that's what שמואל Shmuel says וזו באה
מטיפה פסולה v'zu ba mi-tipa psula ורבי יוחנן אמר v'Rabbi Yochanan amar
ישא אדם בת דומה ולא ישא דומה. yisa adam bat duma v'lo
yisa duma. No better to marry the daughter. שזו עומדת בחזקת כשרות,
she-zu omedet b'chezkat kashrut, there's no reason to suspect the daughter she
has a חזקה chazaka of being
כשרה ksheira וזו אינה עומדת בחזקת כשרות v'zu eina omedet b'chezkat kashrut
and the mother though is suspected of committing adultery. Now of course...
Actually that's bizarre and some of the פוסקים poskim point out what
do you mean? The mother started off she was כשר kasher and
you have a suspicion whether she committed adultery. So she has a
חזקת כשרות. chezkas kashrus. The daughter hasn't been born yet, and the
board- and the daughter was born under a cloud of suspicion. So
the daughter דווקא davka doesn't have a חזקת כשרות. chezkas kashrus. She
might be a ממזרת. mamzeres. You never knew that she started with
an acceptable status. But again, that's looking at it halachically. Looking at
it in terms of character, it's like who- you know, the- if
they're gossiping about the mother, whatever she- there's probably there's something going
on. I mean, maybe she didn't commit adultery, but there's, you know,
clearly questions about her character. The daughter, there's no questions about the
daughter's character. So halachically as a ממזרת mamzeres is a different question.
But if you focus on the issue of character, there's no questions
about the daughter's character.
But the גמרא Gemara thought these things, you know, like that these
things somehow did transfer.
Nevertheless, the daughter, the daughter might be from- from her husband.
No, no, I understand, that's true, but that's the point- no, that's
the point.
The point is if you knew the daughter, you don't know the
mother committed adultery, even if the mother committed adultery, you don't know
whether the child was the child of such an act. So that's
the point. Okay? Alright, so there's a big question mark here, but
it's a question mark on the mother's character as opposed to a
question mark on the daughter's, you know, nature of the daughter's birth.
Okay? So that's the debate. Okay? So מיתיבי, Meisive, says the גמרא.
Gemara.
נושא אדם דומה. Nosei adam duma. So we have a ברייתא, braisa,
a man can marry a דומה. duma. So you see that proves
like who- what was it? Like שמואל Shmuel that it's permissible.
The question is, doesn't say he can't
marry- alright, so as the גמרא's Gemara gonna say, as the גמרא's
Gemara gonna say. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so anyways the גמרא
Gemara says, it seems like we're saying like שמואל Shmuel that you
marry a דומה duma and you don't marry a בת דומה. bas
duma. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, ותסברא? v'tisbra? Does that make sense?
נושא לכתחילה? Nosei l'chatchila? Really? Like, that's top of the priority list,
is to marry a דומה? duma? So אלא, ella, no, what it
means is אם נשא im nasa it's okay. If you married, it's
acceptable. It doesn't mean you're allowed, you should or whatever. So וכן
תניא נמי בת דומה. V'chein tanya nami bas duma. So we're not
saying a דומה duma over a בת דומה. bas duma. We're saying
בדיעבד, b'diavad, if you married, it's acceptable. You're not gonna פסול posul
the- the wedding. So the same would be true about a בת
דומה. bas duma. It's not telling you clearly what the preference is.
והלכתא, V'hilchasa, and the הלכה halacha is, again, using the phrase והלכתא
V'hilchasa since all we're telling is the preference, interesting phrase here, ישא
אדם בת דומה ואל ישא דומה, yissa adam bas duma v'al yissa
duma, which I think makes the most intuitive sense, right? Better marry
the daughter who- no suspicions were raised about her character. You might
not know who her father is, you maybe she's a ממזרת mamzeres
or there's that whole ביאה פסולה bia psula טיפה פסולה tipa psula
question, but ultimately there's no questions about her character. As opposed to,
right, ואל ישא דומה, v'al yissa duma, not the דומה, duma, that
there are questions about her character. So thankfully in the end the
גמרא Gemara goes in favor of the concern of character, observed character
traits, rather than the concern of, you know, about biology and who
the father is, or is she a ממזרת. mamzeres. דתני רב תחליפא
בר מערבא קמיה דרבי אבהו, Detani Rav Tachlifa bar Maarava kamei d'Rabbi
Abbahu, אישה מזנה בניה כשרים, Isha m'zana baneiha k'sheirim, רוב בעילות אחר
הבעל. rov beilos achar habaal. Now here's though another reason, not just
what I said, but maybe now addressing the halachic issue. You don't
have to be concerned that the daughter is a ממזר, mamzer, because
even when a woman commits
adultery and we know that she's committed adultery, we assume that the
children are כשרים k'sheirim because most of the time she's still having
sex with her husband. Which is actually interesting because, you know, sometimes
if a woman is having an affair, she winds up having- or
I don't know, a man, whoever's having the affair- winds up having
a lot less sex with their spouse. So but the גמרא Gemara
says nevertheless you sort of assume that even if that happened, it
happened maybe a few times, it doesn't make you suspect whose child
it is.
Wait a second, wait, if this is a married woman, children- an
adulterous union are what?
No. If you know a woman committed adultery, you have no idea
whose child she is- is bearing. You can assume it is the
husband's child. Okay, so now we seem to be shifting again from
the question of character to the halachic question. You can marry the
daughter of a woman that's being gossiped about because you can assume
that the child is not a ממזר. mamzer. בעי רמי בר חמא,
Ba'ei Rami bar Chama, היתה פרוצה ביותר מהו. haysa prutza b'yoser mahu.
Let's say she was very licentious. Like, she- you know, she every-
she- like there's a- people are gossiping about her that she's always
being seen with strange men, you know, in hotels or whatever they're
talking about. So what would you say there? How far would you
say that you assume it's the husband's child? So אליבא דמאן דאמר
אין אישה מתעברת אלא סמוך לוסתה לא תיבעי לך. Aliba d'man d'amar
ein isha misaberes ella samuch l'vista lo tibei lach. Now it becomes
very interesting. According to the approach that a woman only gets pregnant
near when she is expecting her period—completely wrong biology, okay—right before she's
expecting her period is when she is not getting pregnant.
It means before or around? No, after.
Well, it's assumed to be right before, because afterwards she's a נידה.
nidda. So then there's no question that we have to be concerned
that it's another man's child. Why? דלא ידעה בה ולא מינטרה לה.
D'lo yada'a bah v'lo mintara lah.
Because the husband doesn't know when exactly the date is that she'll
have her period, which is interesting because all of מסכת... Maseches... מסכת
נדה Masechet Niddah assumes that women have regular periods, but okay, but
there are women who don't have regular periods, so he can't know
for sure. So because he doesn't know for sure when she's getting
when she's going to have her period, he doesn't know for sure
when she'll be fertile, and therefore he's not able to sort of
basically make sure she doesn't leave the house. So this is very
interesting. It assumes that the husband, sometimes the husband's completely oblivious and
everybody else knows, but it assumes that the husband is aware of
these suspicions, but what can he do? He can't control his wife.
Okay, but but minimally he'll make sure she doesn't leave, like like
he's on top of, like he's he's given his eye on her,
you know, during the period when she's fertile. That gets back to
the issue of doesn't want her to be having another man's child.
Okay, so but if it's if he doesn't know exactly when that
period is, he can't control it. So we'd have to be concerned
that if she's פרוצה ביותר prutza b'yoter it might be another man's
child. כי איבעיא לך, ki ibaya lach, what is our question? אליבא
דמאן דאמר אין אשה מתעברת אלא סמוך לטבילתה, aliba d'man d'amar ein
isha mitaberet ela samuch l'tvilata, which actually is the reality. A woman
only gets pregnant near the time she goes to the מקוה, mikveh,
although that's certainly true now that a woman goes to the מקוה
mikveh about 12 days after the onset of the of the period,
then it really is very very close to going to the מקוה.
mikveh. According to the הלכה halacha of the of according to the
תורה, Torah, which was, you know, where it was seven days after
the onset, it wouldn't be so close to, but it still would
be in the in the period around that. According to that, then
the husband knows when is her fertile period. מאי, mai, what would
we say? כיון דידע בה נטורי מנטר לה, keivan d'yada bah naturi
mintar lah, since he knows that when she's going to be fertile,
he's going to be watching her, at least for that period. או
דילמא, o dilma, or do we say כיון דפרוצה ביותר לא, keivan
d'prutza b'yoter lo, no, because she's very פרוצה, prutza, she's very, you
know, again, I'm missing the right word here, licentious is the word
that comes to me, but that's not I don't think the exact
right word. Anyway, he can't control her, even though he knows when
this is happening and he's aware of what she's doing, you know,
she's just going to just, you know, she she'll walk out on
him, he can't control her. So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku,
we don't know. Okay, so this shifted from this question of, I
think fascinating, going from this question of character, a woman of observed
character as opposed to the child where there's no problematically observed character,
but maybe you don't know who the father is, maybe she's a
ממזרת, mamzeret, so but not from a הלכה halacha standpoint, from a
character standpoint. In that case, we say no, no, no, the observed
character is clearly the bigger problem. And from the הלכה halacha standpoint
though, at what stage do you start being concerned that a woman's
children are not her own when there's rumors, etc., or even if
you know she committed adultery, at what stage does that raise questions
about her children? You know, that becomes a very interesting question.
Yeah, and I mean, even before we had discussions about עוברת דת,
overet dat, which you know it's just, alright maybe she's not covering
her hair correctly, and then he can keep her. But if she's
already you know like the subject of all
this פרוצה ביותר, prutza b'yoter, not just that she's regular פרוצה, prutza,
but... Right. So no one no one like you know came...
Right. So that's discussed in יבמות, Yevamot, how much concrete evidence is
needed that she committed adultery, right you don't need the same evidence
to execute her, but you know you do need something which is
called like עדי כיעור, edei kiyur, okay, witnesses of unseemly actions, you
know. How much evidence is needed to the point where he's where
it's no longer his discretion whether he can stay married to her
or not. Which is very relevant because there are cases where, you
know, it's like it's funny like it comes up in different גמרות.
Gemarot. At the end of נדרים Nedarim we dealt with a case
where a woman says she committed adultery, and the הלכה halacha is
she's not believed, which actually is very and then maybe she's trying
to force a divorce, exactly, very helpful in dealing with a couple
that wants to reconcile. On the other hand, you know, you've got
cases where like I know cases about about somebody who suspects his
wife of committing adultery, and he hired a private eye, and the
guy went and he took like got photographs and the whole thing,
you know, and then they decided they wanted to reconcile. So that
was like a lot harder to deal with, right? Because, you know,
because there there was like this concrete עדי כיעור, edei kiyur, so
even though nobody saw enough of the exact act enough that she
could be like, you know, executed based on, you know, there was
like you know what you see him going into a hotel to
a motel together and this and that, like at what stage is
it like, you know, is that that halachically they can't stay together.
That's an important question, yes.
This is also a שיטה shita from the jealousy with the סוטה
Sotah case. Now the husband's not jealous at all, it's just a
question of...
No, the husband divorced her, or he died. This is another or
he died, this is now another guy. Oh, oh you mean in
the last case. He might be jealous but...
There's nothing about סוטה Sotah here.
Right, right. No, the early cases was that the woman who had
been suspected of committing adultery was now free, maybe the husband husband
either died or divorced her and the question is somebody else wants
to marry her. But in this case at the end, about the
status of the daughter, you've got a woman who the husband knows
is cheating on him and there's very little he's able to do
about it.
But there's no raising of jealousy.
Yeah, I know, it's you're right, it's like interesting to present that
other phenomenon. Right.
One wonders why he doesn't divorce her because he could divorce her
here without a כתובה, ketubah, you know. All right. ואלו שבית דין,
v'elu she'Beit Din, the following are the ones that בית דין Beit
Din can, you know, be מקנא mekane on their behalf. So תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, איש, ish, it says
איש איש כי תשטה אשתו. ish ish ki tisteh ishto. sound mind
or חרש cheresh a deaf mute, not seen as of you know
being capable, and in these cases where שילך בעלה למדינת הים shelach
ba'alah limdinas hayam he's just not present, ושהיה חבוש בבית האסורין veshehayah
chavush beveiss ha'asurin he's either overseas or he's in prison,
if he's not physically present, שבית דין מקנאין להם ופוסלין מכתובתן, shebeis
din mikanein lahem ufoslin mikesubasan,
בית דין beis din can step in and do קינוי kinui on
behalf of their husbands in order that they'll learn their lose their
כתובה kesubah when their husbands come back. So the גמרא Gemara says
יכול אף להשקותה, yachol af lehashkosah, maybe בית דין beis din can
even go through and make them drink the water, תלמוד לומר והביא
האיש את אשתו talmud lomar veheivi ha'ish es ishto and it doesn't
say איש איש, ish ish, so no, it has to be the
husband that brings her. רבי יוסי Rebi Yosi says אף להשקותה ולכשייצא
בעלה מבית האסורין ישקנה, af lehashkosah ulechsheyeitzei ba'alah mibeiss ha'asurin yashkenah, no,
the בית דין beis din can't make her drink, but the husband,
if he ever gets better or returns, he can make her drink
on the force of the בית דין's beis din קינוי. kinui. במאי
קמיפלגי, Bimei kamifligi, what's the debate?
Should not do it on by send a שליח, shaliach, right? If
I can say, listen, you're a good friend of mine and I
suspect my wife, I'm going to be in prison, could you keep
an eye on her and if
anything's seen, yeah, it does not think that although it does before
the גמרא Gemara used the concept of בית דין beis din sort
of as doing it on his behalf and is type of a
זכין zachin etc. It does seem like it's that's a good point
that it's specifically a power of בית דין beis din like you
cannot be ממנה שליח. memaneh shaliach. So במאי קמיפלגי, bimei kamifligi, what's
the debate? רבנן סברי Rabanan savri בעינן וקינא והביא, beeinan vekina veheivi,
the same man who does the קינוי kinui has to be the
one who brings his wife. רבי יוסי סבר Rebi Yosi savar לא
בעינן וקינא והביא, lo beeinan vekina veheivi, no, as long as the
קינוי kinui is done legitimately, somebody else can do the he as
long as the קינוי kinui is done by בית דין beis din
that was legitimate, he can be the והביא. veheivi. תנו רבנן: Tanna
rabanan: אשר תשטה אשה תחת אישה, asher tisteh ishah tachas ishah, that
a woman strays from her husband,
להקיש איש לאשה ואשה לאיש lehakish ish le'ishah ve'ishah le'ish to say
that the man and the women have to be in the same
category. למאי הלכתא, Lemei hilchesa, for what purpose? אמר רב ששת, Amar
Rav Sheshes, כשם שהוא סומא לא היה משקה, ksheim sheim hu suma
lo hayah mashkeh, the same way if he was blind he can't
make her drink,
דכתיב ונסתרה, dicsiv venistarah, it's like we are trying to more and
more narrow the possible category. ומנעלם מעיני אישה, uminalam me'einei ishah, it
was hidden from the husband's eyes, which means normally he can see,
כך היא אם היתה סומא לא הייתה שותה. kach hi im haysah
suma lo haysah shosah. So if she was blind, she it would
be she'd be excluded. וביסי אומר Ubeisi omer כשם שחיגרת וגידמת לא
הייתה שותה, ksheim shechigeres veigidemes lo haysah shosah, the same way that
if she is not, you know, does not have her legs or
her arms, she cannot be made to drink, דכתיב והעמיד הכהן dicsiv
vehe'emid hakohein that he shall make her stand את האשה, es ha'ishah,
excuse me, לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, so she has to be able
to stand, ונתן על כפיה venasan al kapeha put on her hands
the מנחה, minchah, so she has to have hands, כך הוא אם
היה חיגר או גידם, kach hu im hayah chiger o gidem, similarly
if he did not have his legs or he was lame or
he did not have his arms, לא היה משקה, lo hayah mashkeh,
he would not be able to make her drink. מר בר רב
אשי אמר, Mar bar Rav Ashi amar, כשם שאלמת לא הייתה שותה,
ksheim she'ilemes lo haysah shosah, the same way if she was mute
she should not drink, דכתיב ואמרה האשה אמן אמן, dicsiv veamrah ha'ishah
amein amein, כך אם הוא היה אלם לא היה משקה, kach im
hu hayah ileim lo hayah mashkeh, similarly he would not. Okay, הדרן
עלך המקנא, hadran alach hamekae, that was the end of a fascinating
פרק perek that dealt with what type of man, what type of
woman, what type of marriage is in the פרשה parsha of סוטה.
Sotah. Let us now get to, I'm sorry, דוסא. Dosa. Let us
get to the next פרק perek which is the process, the effects
of the water. I mean, in a way we've dealt with the
effects of the water, but we're going to be broadening it a
little and then we're joining also being digressing significantly about דרשות, drashos,
so let's take a look. I know. So the whole the whole
remainder of the עמוד amud here is a משנה, mishnah, which is
good because we only have 12 minutes.
כשם שהמים בודקין אותה, כך המים בודקין אותו. ksheim shehamayim bodkin osah
kach hamayim bodkin oso, The same way the water checks her, it
checks him, שנאמר ובאו ובאו. shene'emar uvau uvau. Now who is the
him? Any guess who the him is?
The בועל? boel?
Right. So you might have thought because we said before that the
same way she has to be מנוקה מעוון, menukah me'avon, he has
to be מנוקה מעוון, menukah me'avon, and it means the husband. So
why would it check the husband? It could check the husband if,
for example, he had other sexual sin in general or it could
check the husband if he slept with her after she was a
סוטה, sotah, maybe he'd be punished. But no, but the גמרא Gemara
is going to say that it means the בועל. boel. So when
the water goes through her, makes her explode, whoever he is, he's
also basically going to
explode. Okay. Blow, distend, blow up, okay. כשם שהמים בודקין אותה ksheim
shehamayim bodkin osah, כך המים בודקין אותו, kach hamayim bodkin oso. שנאמר
ובאו ובאו. shene'emar uvau uvau. It will go in and go in,
so it will go into even the man wherever he might be.
I'm sorry, it says ובאו uvau twice? ובאו ובאו המים המאררים ובאו
המים, uvau uvau hamayim hamarerim uvau hamayim, not right next to each
other, it says it in different פסוקים. pesukim. כשם שאסורה לבעל כך
אסורה לבועל, ksheim sheasurah leba'al kach asurah leboel, the same way when
she is a סוטה, sotah, when she is a סוטה sotah before
the water checked her, before the water checked her, she is forbidden
to her husband and we learn from the
word ונטמאה. venisamah. So therefore even if the husband let's say divorces
her or dies and never went through the process, she never gets
cleared, she can then not she is then forbidden similarly to the
man she is suspected of committing adultery with. By the way, I
should say that this is also very relevant... So what do you
do about the case that a woman and her husband are getting
divorced, maybe they have a civil divorce, she goes ahead and
she it's been years she's waiting for her גט, get, she starts
marrying she's living with another man, and then she finally gets the
גט get from her husband. So technically during the time she's been
living with this other man she's been committing adultery halachically because she
doesn't have a גט, get, and now it should say אסור לבעל
ואסור לבועל, assur l'ba'al v'assur l'bo'el, and now even though she has
a גט, get, she shouldn't be allowed to marry this guy because
this was a man that she slept with while she was married
to her husband. So that's the הלכה Halacha whether she is known
to have committed adultery she's forbidden or the man she's suspected of
committing adultery with, as long as the water has not done their
job, she's forbidden to the בועל bo'el the same way it to
the
בעל, ba'al, שנאמר ונטמאה ונטמאה, shene'emar venitme'ah venitme'ah, דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei
Rabbi Akiva, the extra ו vav ונטמאה, venitme'ah,
it's one of the פסוקים pesukim tells us that even to the
second even to the other guy she's טמאה. tme'ah. אמר רבי יהושע
קצץ, amar Rabbi Yehoshua Katzatz, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, כך היה
דורש זכריה בן הקצב. kach hayah doresh Zecharya ben HaKatzav. So this
is what זכריה בן הקצב Zecharya ben HaKatzav used to say, this
extra ו, vav, but רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, but רבי Rabbi says,
שני פעמים אמור בפרשה נטמאה ונטמאה, shnei pe'amim amur b'parsha nitme'ah venitme'ah,
it's not the ו vav that we דורשים, dorshin, it's the fact
that it says נטמאה nitme'ah twice, אחד לבעל ואחד לבועל. echad l'ba'al
v'echad l'bo'el. Okay, so you learn it from a ו vav or
you learn it from an extra word. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
goes on and says בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, bo bayom darash
Rabbi Akiva, on that same day רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva made the
following דרשה. drasha. Now רש"י Rashi points out that the גמרא Gemara
in ברכות Brachos says whenever it says בו ביום, bo bayom, it's
when רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah was made the
ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva over רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and he basically
opened up the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was
very much of an elitist and he said only somebody who is
תוכו כברו, tocho k'baro, somebody who we know is totally pure on
the inside and the outside, and the גמרא, Gemara, well let's read
it in רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi quotes the גמרא Gemara says it
better than I can. בו ביום דרש, bo bayom darash, the גמרא
Gemara says right across from where it says ויקרא י"א, Vayikra Yud
Aleph, מסכת ברכות אמרינן, Masechet Brachos amrina, דכל היכא דתני בו ביום
הוא יום שהושיבו רבי אלעזר בן עזריה לנשיאות, d'chol heicha detani bo
bayom hu yom shehoshivu Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah l'nesiyus,
when he was made the נשיא, Nasi, שנתרבו תלמידים shenisrabu talmidim and
then there were many students who were welcomed into the בית מדרש,
Beis Medrash, שנתנו רשות ליכנס לכל, shenatnu reshus likanes lakol, שרבן גמליאל
אמר כל תלמיד חכם שאין תוכו כברו אל יכנס לבית המדרש, sheRabban
Gamliel amar kol talmid chacham she-ein tocho k'baro al yikanes l'beis hamedrash,
whose inside is not like the outside, don't enter the בית מדרש.
Beis Medrash. ורבתה תורה בו ביום, verabta Torah bo bayom, and on
that day that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said everybody who wants to
can come in, והיתה הלכה תלויה בבית המדרש שלא פירשוה, v'haysah Halacha
tluyah b'veis hamedrash shelo peirshuha, and since there were so many people,
you were allowed so many different voices, right, everything became clarified. והא
דתני הכא, vehad detani hacha,
so why is it being taught
here
בו ביום? bo bayom? נראה בעיני nir'eh b'einay דהך דרשה dehach drasha
דנטמאה ונטמאה de'nitme'ah venitme'ah דלעיל dele'eil בו ביום נמי הוי. bo bayom
nami havay. Maybe the ונטמאה ונטמאה venitme'ah venitme'ah was that day,
so these are things that also were on the same day. Either
way, it's going to be interesting cases where there's going to be
a דרשה drasha and then like a response to a דרשה. drasha.
Let's take a look.
By the way, it's just מאי משמע דדרשינן מבינייהו. mai mashma darshinan
m'beineihu.
Right, but
let's take a look, but the next debate will be more interesting
about what people think about רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva hermeneutics. So let's
take a look. בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, bo bayom darash Rabbi
Akiva, on that day רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva explicated. וכלי חרש אשר
יפול מהם אל תוכו כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. ucheli cheres asher yipol
mehem el tocho kol asher b'tocho yitma.
So this is talking about
if a שרץ, sheretz, like a dead rodent, falls into a pottery
vessel, anything in the vessel becomes טמא. tamei. אינו אומר טמא, eino
omer tamei, it will become טמא, tamei, אלא יטמא, ela yitma, shall
become טמא tamei לטמא אחרים, l'tamei acherim, make others טמא. tamei. לימד
על כיכר שני שמטמא
את השלישי.
limed al kikar sheni
shemetamei es hashlishi.
A כיכר kikar which is
a שני sheni can make a שלישי. shlishi.
What does it mean? It means here you've got your כלי חרש,
cli cheres, okay, open it up so it's open, exactly here you've
got your כלי חרש, cli cheres, here we'll do it with this
which is, here you've got your כלי חרש. cli cheres. So if
you've got a שרץ sheretz in here, okay, even in the air,
it makes the כלי טמא, kli tamei, so the שרץ sheretz is
an אב, av, the כלי kli is a ראשון. rishon. Anything else
in the כלי kli gets טומאה tumah from the כלי, kli, so
if the כלי kli is a ראשון, rishon, the thing that gets
טומאה tumah is a שני. sheni. That's why it's only by food,
וכל האוכל, vekol ha-ochel, remember only food can be a שני. sheni.
Okay, so that's how we learned that food becomes a שני. sheni.
Now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says but it doesn't say the food
becomes טמא, tamei, it says יטמא, yitma, shall become טמא, tamei, but
he's reading it as יטמא yitamei can now make other things טמא.
tamei. So you see that the כיכר kikar which is a שני
sheni can make something else into a שלישי. shlishi. So this is
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva דרשה drasha that actually the real הלכה Halacha
is and the הלכה Halacha we פסקן pasken is that only תרומה
Terumah can be a שלישי, shlishi, but רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva learning
from this that anything can be a שלישי. shlishi. The food becomes
a שני sheni to make other things into a שלישי. shlishi. Okay.
לטמא אחרים לימד על כיכר שני שמטמא את השלישי. l'tamei acherim limed
al kikar sheni shemetamei es hashlishi.
אמר רבי יהושע, amar Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, מי
גלה עפר מעיניך רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, mi gala afar me'einecha Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai, who will remove the dust from your eyes, רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, שהיית אומר, she'hayisa omer, you
used to say, maybe it means because he was dead at that
time, so he has to be taken out of the ground and
the dust removed from his eyes. I'm not being non-serious, what does
that idiom 'who will remove the dust from his eyes', okay, if
only you were alive to see this might be a way of,
I'm serious, that might be what it means, like if only you
could get the dust out of your eyes and see what just
happened right now. Okay. שהיית אומר she hayita omer you used to
say עתידה רחל לטהר כיכר שלישי שאין לו מקרא מן התורה atidah
Rachel l'taher kikar shlishi she'ein lo mikra min haTorah that we say
that the fact that food can become a שלישי shlishi even תרומה
terumah is not explicit. And we only learn it from a קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. And you were concerned that a if it's only
a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, it's not explicit, a later generation will
say that food even תרומה terumah cannot be a שלישי. shlishi. You
were concerned about that. שהוא טמא. she'hu tamei. We don't have a
פסוק pasuk that tells you it's טמא. tamei. So look Rabbi Akiva,
your student Rabbi Akiva, look what your student Rabbi Akiva just did.
מצא לו מקרא מן התורה שהוא טמא. matza lo mikra min haTorah
she'hu tamei. He brought a פסוק, pasuk, you should be so happy.
שנאמר she'ne'emar כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. kol asher b'tocho yitma. Okay, that
was a good response. בו ביום bo bayom on the same day
דרש רבי עקיבא darash Rabbi Akiva ומדותם מחוץ לעיר פאת קדמה אלפיים
באמה. u'madotem mi'chutz la'ir pe'at kedma alpayim ba'amah.
So this is the city of the לויים. Levi'im. So you outside
the city you have 2,000 אמות. amot. That's one פסוק pasuk that
they get. ומקרא אחר אומר u'mikra acher omer another פסוק pasuk says
מקיר העיר וחוצה אלף אמה mikier ha'ir v'chutza elef amah they get
1,000 אמות amot סביב. saviv. אי אפשר לומר אלף אמה שכבר נאמר
אלפיים באמה. ee efshar lomar elef amah she'kvar ne'emar alpayim ba'amah. ואי
אפשר לומר אלפיים באמה שכבר נאמר אלף אמה. v'ee efshar lomar alpayim
ba'amah she'kvar ne'emar elef amah. So what is it? 2,000 or 1,000?
הכיצד ha'keitzad how do you reconcile it? אלף אמה מגרש elef amah
migrash so the 1,000 אמה amah is like a, you know, is
the open fields. ואלפיים באמה v'alpayim ba'amah the 2,000 אמות amot is
not what they actually get as part of their city as the
they don't get the real estate, but תחום שבת tchum Shabbat that's
the boundaries, the outer boundaries of their city and we learn the
idea that there's a תחום שבת tchum Shabbat of 2,000 אמות. amot.
So the city limits I guess is what we would say. It
doesn't mean it owns that they own that property but that's the
city limits and that's where you get the idea of 2,000 אמות.
amot. No, it's not an additional 2,000 אמות amot because it's just
because the houses stop, the houses in the city and then you
get 1,000 and then another 1,000. It's 2,000 from where the house
ends. Okay. It's not 3,000.
It's אלפיים באמה alpayim ba'amah includes this אלף אמה.
elef amah. Yes. Okay. And 2,000 where the house ends. So the
city limits are 2,000 אמות amot and that's where you get the
idea of תחום שבת. tchum Shabbat. Okay. That's what he says. רבי
אלעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר Rabbi Elazar beno shel Rabbi
Yose HaGlili omer Rabbi Elazar the son of Rabbi Yose HaGlili says
אלף אמה מגרש ואלפיים באמה שדות וכרמים. elef amah migrash v'alpayim ba'amah
sadot u'chramim.
No.
1,000 אמה amah is מגרש migrash like empty fields, it's like you
know nice manicured lawns or whatever it would be. You know and
then the extra 1,000 אמות amot the 2,000 אמות amot the so
you know the it is going to be that extra 1,000 אמות
amot that's going to be where you actually get fields and vineyards.
So you know they would plow it but you wouldn't have your
field right against the city. You'd have a little bit of a
break.
Okay so in both cases you only get 2,000 אמות, amot, right?
No. What do you mean? Rabbi Elazar the son of Rabbi Yose
HaGlili says that they get a lot of real estate that Rabbi
Akiva says they don't get.
Rabbi Akiva says the only real estate they get is 1,000 אמות.
amot. The area after that, the next 1,000 אמות amot is just
the definition of city limits. It's not that the city owns that
real estate. And Rabbi Elazar the son of Rabbi Yose says no,
they own that real estate and they use it for fields and
vineyards.
Okay but it's still 2,000, no one's saying it's 3,000. Correct, correct.
בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva on that
day Rabbi Akiva explained אז ישיר משה ובני ישראל את השירה הזאת
לה' ויאמרו לאמר az yashir Moshe u'vnei Yisrael et hashirah hazot l'Hashem
v'yomru leimor שאין תלמוד לומר לאמר she'ein talmud lomar leimor it didn't
have to say לאמר leimor because it said ויאמרו. v'yomru. ומה תלמוד
לומר לאמר u'ma talmud lomar leimor מלמד שהיו ישראל עונים שירה אחר
משה. melamed she'hayu Yisrael onim shirah acharei Moshe.
There was a responsive reading. ויאמרו לאמר v'yomru leimor like he said
to be responded to or something. על כל דבר ודבר כקורא את
ההלל al kol davar v'davar k'korei et haHallel like they would read
the Hallel. ולכך נאמר לאמר. u'l'kach ne'emar leimor. They would answer. Like
Hallel? Well, we'll see about this in the גמרא. Gemara. רבי נחמיה
אומר כקורא את שמע ולא כקורא את ההלל. Rabbi Nechemia omer k'korei
et Shma v'lo k'korei et haHallel. No, it'd be like you would
read the שמע. Shma. So exactly what the debate is, we'll see
in the גמרא. Gemara. בו ביום bo bayom on that day דרש
רבי יהושע בן הורקנוס darash Rabbi Yehoshua ben Horkenos לא עבד איוב
את הקדוש ברוך הוא אלא מאהבה. lo avad Iyov et haKadosh Baruch
Hu ela me'ahava. Iyov served God not from fear because it says
היה ירא אלהים haya yereh Elokim it says in the beginning, but
ultimately it was out of love. שנאמר she'ne'emar הן יקטלני hen yiktaleni
even if he will kill me לא איחל lo ayachel to him
I will long. ועדיין הדבר שקול v'adayin hadavar shakol but still it's
balanced, it's indeterminate. לו אני מצפה או איני מצפה. lo ani m'tzapeh
o eini m'tzapeh. Will I yearn for him or not yearn for
him? Now what do you mean? What's the question? The question is
that the כתיב ktiv is לא lo with an אלף. alef. The
קרי keri is לו lo with a ואו. vav. So if he
kill me I will not longer long for him or I will
still long for him. Okay. So you don't know. תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar עד אגוע לא אסיר תומתי ממני ad egva lo asir tumati
mimeni
even until death my righteousness will not swerve from me. So even
if I die as a result I will still remain steadfast, which
means it's out of love. מלמד שמאהבה עשה. melamed she'me'ahava asa. אמר
רבי יהושע amar Rabbi Yehoshua Rabbi Joshua says, and this now brackets
the statement similar to this above: מי יגלה עפר מעיניך רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי mi yigaleh afar me'einecha Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai who will
remove the dust from your eyes Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai שהיית דורש
כל ימיך שלא עבד איוב את המקום אלא מיראה. she'hayita doresh kol
yamecha she'lo avad Iyov et haMakom ela mi'yirah. You used to say
it was only out of fear. שנאמר איש תם וישר ירא אלהים
וסר מרע. she'ne'emar ish tam v'yashar yereh Elokim v'sar me'ra. והלא יהושע
תלמיד תלמידך v'halo Yehoshua talmid talmidecha look at Yehoshua, the student of
your student, Rabbi Akiva's student, your grand-student. לימד שמאהבה עשה. limed she'me'ahava
asa.
He learned that he did it out of love.
It was like he should be זוכה zocheh to see this? Even
though he disagreed with you.
Right. At a good point. Okay. We'll continue tomorrow. I also want
us to pick up tomorrow I want to look quickly at the
תוספות Tosafot who quotes some interesting ירושלמי Yerushalmi about this מים בור.
mayim bor. Sure you're his student's student, רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva*'s student, your grandson, למה דאהבה *lama de'ahava*, so he learned
that he did it out of love. Yeah, you know like you
should be so זוכה *zocheh* to see this? You know he just
agreed with you. Right, exactly, that's a good point. Okay, to be
continued tomorrow. I also want us to pick up tomorrow, I want
to look quickly at the תוספות *Tosfos* who quotes some interesting ירושלמים
*Yerushalmis* about this מים בודקין אותו *mayim botkin oso*. All right, we'll
stop here. Okay, it's 9:00, let's pick it up. Everyone have a
wonderful day. All right, we're going to start now דף ל"ד *daf
lamed daled*. We're on the top of ל"ד עמוד א' *lamed daled
amud alef*. We are beginning a brand new פרק *perek*, the fourth
פרק *perek* of מסכת סוטה *Masechet Sotah*. פרק היה מביא *Perek Hayah
Movee*. If you're following on the Artscroll it's 24a1. משנה *Mishna*. היה
מביא את מנחתה בכפיפה של מצרי *Hayah movee es minchasah be'kififah shel
mitzri*, ונותנה על ידיה כדי ליגעה *ve'nosnah al yadeha kedei le'yage'ah*. כל
המנחות תחילתן וסופן בכלי שרת *Col ha'minchos techilasun ve'sofam bi'kli shareis*, וזו
תחילתה בכפיפה של מצרי וסופה בכלי שרת *ve'zo techilasah bi'kififah shel mitzri
ve'sofah bi'kli shareis*. כל המנחות טעונות שמן ולבונה *Col ha'minchos te'unos shemen
u'levonah*, וזו אינה טעונה לא שמן ולא לבונה *ve'zo ainah te'unah lo
shemen ve'lo levonah*. כל המנחות באות מן החיטין *Col ha'minchos ba'os min
ha'chittin*, וזו באה מן השעורים *ve'zo ba'ah min ha'se'orim*. מנחת העומר *Minchas
ha'omer*, אף על פי שבאה מן השעורים *af al pi she'ba'ah min
ha'se'orim*, היא היה באה גרשו *hee hayah ba'ah gersu*, וזו היה באה
קמח חימטין *ve'zo hayah ba'ah kemach chimtin*. רבן גמליאל אומר *Rabban Gamliel
omer*, כשם שמעשיה מעשה בהמה *ke'shem she'ma'aseha ma'aseh behemah*, כך קרבנה מעשה
בהמה *kach korbanah ma'aseh behemah*.